Guide to the KUHT Film and Video
University of Houston Libraries
KUHT Film and Video
1950-2000
1960-1990
1997-006
KUHT-TV (Television station: Houston, Tex.)
465.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The KUHT Collection includes film reels, videotapes, correspondence, memoranda, publications, clippings, photographs, and related material dating from the 1950s through the 1990s. The bulk of the material dates from the mid-1960s to 1990s with a few photographs dating to the early to mid-1950s.
Historical Note:
KUHT-TV debuted on May 25, 1953, as America's first educational television station. Since then it has served as a model for other educational television stations. Its main goal is to provide quality programming to students, faculty, and the entire community. KUHT predates the Corporation for Public Broadcasting (CPB) and the Public Broadcasting System (PBS). Its history includes award-winning local and national productions, including a national Emmy Award for excellence. KUHT is licensed to the University of Houston, and is located in the LeRoy and Lucile Melcher Center for Public Broadcasting located at 4343 Elgin, on the northeast corner of the main campus.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
GRETA (Organization: Texas); KUHT Film Productions; KUHT-TV (Television station: Houston, Tex.); Public Broadcasting Service (U.S.); University of Houston
Genre/Form of Material:
Videocassettes
Topical Term:
Television -- Production and direction
Accruals:
Additional 236 unprocessed boxes acquired July 11, 2014.
Additional unprocessed boxes arrived in September 2015.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Digital Collections:
KUHT Highlights digital collection (http://digital.lib.uh.edu/collection/p15195coll38)
KUHT Film and Video in the UH Libraries Audio/Video Repository (https://av.lib.uh.edu/?f%5Bcollection_ssim%5D%5B%5D=KUHT+Film+and+Video)
Scope and Contents
The KUHT Collection includes film reels, videotapes, correspondence, memoranda, publications, clippings, photographs, and related material dating from the 1950s through the 1990s. The bulk of the material dates from the mid-1960s to 1990s with a few photographs dating to the early to mid-1950s.
Please contact the collection curator Emily Vinson (evinson@uh.edu) for further information regarding all film and video material.
The series in the Collection include: Discrepancy Files, Development and Production Files by Jim Fisher and Paul Yeager, Gulf Region Education Television Affiliates (GRETA), Photographs, Ephemera, and Awards.
Visit the University of Houston Libraries Audio/Video Repository to access more than 750 videos from the KUHT Collection. Digitization and access for these items was made possible by grants from the U.S. Institute of Museum and Library Services and Texas State Library and Archives Commission (2017) and Recordings at Risk from the Council on Library and Information Resources (CLIR) made possible by funding from The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation (2019).
Detailed List of Contents
- Documentaries and Features
  - Big Thicket: Crossroads in the Texas Forest, 1985
    Produced documentary as well as 136 film elements.
  - Bill Elliot: Man of Vision, approximately 1971-1974
  - H. L. Hunt: The Richest and the Rightest
  - Inside the Texas Legislature
  - Journey to the Sky: A History of the Alabama and Coushatta Indians of Texas, 1981
    Produced documentary as well as 227 film elements.
  - Medal of Honor
  - The Wrong End of Main
  - 40,000 Window Panes, 1986
  - An historic visit, Una visita historica, 1995
  - Armand Bayou
    59 tapes including produced documentary and work tapes.
  - The Bilingual Education Controversy: A Houston Perspective, March 18, 1982
  - Buffalo, Canebrakers, and Old Texas Love Songs, 1983
  - Black Family Portrait: Building Bridges for Tomorrow, February 20, 1987
  - Blowout: A Special Report, 1979
  - The Changing of the Guard: The Inauguration of Ann Richards, January 15, 1991
  - Channel 8: 30th Anniversary Special
  - Confrontation at Hidalgo
  - Convention!
  - A Cronkite Perspective, 1983
  - The Cruiser Houston Of Pride And Purpose
    105 tapes including produced documentary and work tapes.
  - Formosa of Democracy
    62 tapes.
  - Fresh Paint: The Houston School
  - Greener pastures: A story of the Norwegian community in Bosque Country, Texas, 1987
  - Honor Squadron
    Produced documentary and 269 work tapes including interviews and footage frome “Wings Over Houston 1993” and “Wings Over Midland.”
  - Indochinese Experience in Houston, April, 12 1983
  - The Judys, May 18, 1981
  - Last Stand of the Buffalo, 1984
  - Legacy in Sound - The Struggle, September 30, 1977
  - Life Along the Channel
    12 tapes including produced program and work tapes.
  - Living with AIDs & AIDs II: Challenges of Grief
  - Love of the Game: Baseball in Houston
  - Norway - Oil Across the Water
    8 tapes including produced program and work tapes.
  - The Old Cotton Exchange Building: A mini-history
  - Our Nation's Highest Honor: Remembering World War II's Finest
  - The Perfect Crime (Child Abuse Special)
  - Public Housing: Other End of the Rainbow, October 13, 1981
  - The Ranchers
  - Save the Males
    5 tapes.
  - Something Out of Nothing: A Portrait of Six Houston Artists
  - Space Station: A Three Part Journey
    294 tapes including produced program and work tapes.
  - University of Houston - Dr. Arthur Smith Investiture
    19 tapes.
  - Vietnam: A Season of Healing & Rediscovering The Lost World
    11 tapes.
  - Voices of Discovery
    36 tapes including produced program, work tapes and interviews.
  - The Wall: A World Divided / After the Wall: A World United
    200 tapes including produced program, work tapes and interviews.
  - Wetlands
    Including produced documentary and work tapes.
  - Whence Turtles Come / Turtles II
    33 tapes tapes including produced program and work tapes.
  - Who Will Stand for the 4th Ward?
  - Wit, Grit and Robot Games
    134 tapes including produced program and work tapes.
- Television Series
  - Approaches to the Psychology of Personality, 1957
    Series of interviews with Carl Jung hosted by University of Houston psychology professor Dr. Richard I. Evans.
    - No. 1: Jung Speaks of Freud
    - No. 5: Dr. Carl G. Jung Personality Development: Basic Concepts, Differences with Freud
    - No. 6: Dr. Carl G. Jung Personality Organization: Fundamental Concepts
    - No. 7
    - No. 8
  - Assignment Houston
    - Low Cost Housing
    - Houston Consolidated
    - Violence; Pornography
    - Opening Montage
  - Biology 161
    - #11 Metabolism and Energy
    - #25 Arthropoda
    - Foundations of Modern Biology
  - Biology 162
    - #3 Synthesis and Nutrition
    - Plant Organization
    - The Plant Kingdom
  - Civil Air Patrol
    - Summer Activities Program
    - The Daybreak Call
  - Civil Defense
    - #1: An Overview
    - #2: The Threat of Communism
    - #3: Weapons in the Nuclear Age
    - #4: Chemical and Biological Warfare
    - #5: Radiation and its Effects
    - #6: Warning & Communication
    - #8: Decontamination
    - #9: Shelter & Evacuation
    - #11: Family Planning I
    - #12: Family Planning II
  - Critical Issues
    - Reverend Burke, approximately 1967
    - Reverend William Lawson "Racial Unrest", approximately 1967
    - P. H. Robinson, approximately 1967
    - Garbage, 1970
  - Dance Instruction Series, 1962
    Houston elementary physical education program.
    - Let's Polka
    - Let's Schottische
    - Let's Waltz
  - Discussion with Richard Evans, 1975-1978
    - Konrad Lorenz's Discussion with Dr. Richard Evans: Aggression
    - Konrad Lorenz's Discussion with Dr. Richard Evans: Motivation
    - Konrad Lorenz's Discussion with Dr. Richard Evans: Motivation
    - R.D. Laing's Discussion with Dr. Richard Evans: Reactions and Reflections
    - Nikolaas Tinbergen's Discussion with Richard Evans: Ethology and Genetic Programming vs. Learning
    - Nikolaas Tinbergen's Discussion with Richard Evans: Unique Contributions, Reflections, Reactions
    - Rollo May's Discussion with Richard Evans: Anxiety, Love, Will, Dying
    - Rollo May's Discussion with Dr. Richard Evans: Maturity and Creativity
    - Rollo May's Discussion with Dr. Richard Evans: Reactions to Psychoanalytic Concepts
  - Doctors in Space, 1956
    - #1: Flight Toward the Stars
    - #4: Living Room in the Void
    - Filmed outs
  - Expedition Houston
    - #1 and #2
    - #5: The Dark Hours
  - Houston Independent School District Board Meeting
    - Segregation, December 10, 1956
    - February 27, 1956
    - 1961
  - InLook
    Three reels.
  - Local Issue
    - Integration: Two Towns in Texas
    - The Use of Tongues, The Laying of Hands
  - Mexicania
    - Molinillo
    - Textil
    - Cochinito
    - Regional Costume
  - Notable Contributors to the Psychology of Personality, 1963-1969
    Series of interviews with leading psychologists of the day by University of Houston psychology professor Dr. Richard I. Evans.
    - #9 Dr. Erich Fromm
    - #10 Dr. Erich Fromm
    - #11 Dr. B. F. Skinner
    - #12 Dr. B. F. Skinner
    - #13 Dr. Gordon W. Allport
    - #14 Dr. Gordon W. Allport
    - #15 Dr. Henry A. Murray
    - #16 Dr. Henry A. Murray
    - #17 Dr. Raymond Cattell
    - #18 Dr. Raymond Cattell
    - #19 Professor Erik Erikson
    - #21 Dr. Gardner Murphy
    - #22 Dr. Gardner Murphy
    - #23 Psychological Dialogue with Playwright Arthur Miller
    - #25 Discussion with Carl Jung
    - #31 Dr. Jean Piaget with Dr. Bärbel Inhelder
    - #32 Dr. Jean Piaget with Dr. Bärbel Inhelder
  - People are Taught to be Different, 1957
    Funded by National Educational Television, People Are Taught to be Different was a 12-part series written and produced by Texas Southern University sociology professor Dr. Henry Allen Bullock, and performed by TSU students. This series was an anthropological study on black life based around the “idea that racial discrimination has to be literally taught, that people are not naturally prejudiced.”
    - Channelizing Aggression
    - The Impact of Personalities
    - Concepts of Death
  - Playways
    - Classroom Activities for Primary Grades
    - Classroom Activities for Intermediate Grades
  - Real World of Economics, 1976-1977
    Six produced episodes featuring notable economists and hosted by Pierre Rinfret and 56 reels of duplicate episodes and production elements.
    - John Connally Discusses Government, Bureaucracy & Freedom
    - Thomas Corcoran Discusses The Political Economy
    - Arthur Okun Discusses Guns and Butter
    - Donald Rumsfeld Discusses War and Prosperity
    - Charles Schultze Discusses Government Spending
    - William Simon Discusses The Private Sector
  - Speciation
    - What is a Species
    - The Formation of Species
  - Target Delinquency, approximately 1961
    - Law Enforcement & Delinquency
    - Provocative Reading & Delinquency
    - Parent’s Responsibility & Delinquency
    - Educational Opportunities & Delinquency
    - Delinquency & Youth Unemployment
    - The Lonely Ones
  - The Way It Is, approximately 1968
    Financial literacy program co-produced by Texas Southern University.
    - Home Buying
    - The Small Loan
  - Individual Episodes
    - Drugs in Perspective
    - Congressman George Bush on Mass Transit in Houston
    - The Gold of the Barrios
    - Los Pastores: A Christmas Miracle Play
    - Militant Liberty
    - The Open Door
    - Pressures to Smoke
    - A Psychology of Creativity
    - Psychology on TV
    - Rice University
    - Smoke? Why Not?
    - Teaching the Brain Damaged Child
    - Wasted Youth
    - The World of Billy Joe
  - A Matter of Time
    6 episodes.
  - Abbey Simon
    15 tapes.
  - After Party
    69 tapes.
  - Against All Odds
    5 episodes.
  - Almanac
    188 tapes including produced episodes, work tapes, demos, etc.
    217 episodes available online (https://av.lib.uh.edu/catalog?utf8=%E2%9C%93&search_field=all_fields&q=almanac). Digitization and access for these items made possible by a grant from the U.S. Institute of Museum and Library Services and Texas State Library and Archives Commission (2017).
  - All Stressed Up and Nowhere to Go
  - Arts Alive!
    402 tapes including produced programs, work tapes, dubs, etc.
  - Asia Society
    4 episodes.
  - Auctions
    130 tapes including produced programs, work tapes, dubs, etc.
  - Balancing Your Life with Ellen Sussman
    23 tapes.
  - Bill Moyers Event
    8 tapes.
  - Bradshaw On:
    50 tapes including produced programs, work tapes, dubs, etc.
  - Bush Foundation Asia Conference
    32 tapes.
  - The Capitol Report
    88 episodes.
    85 episodes available online (https://av.lib.uh.edu/catalog?utf8=%E2%9C%93&search_field=all_fields&q=capitol+report). Digitization and access for these items made possible by a grant from the U.S. Institute of Museum and Library Services and Texas State Library and Archives Commission (2017).
  - CARE
    26 episodes.
  - Centerstage
    15 tapes including produced programs and work tapes.
  - Children's Bookshelf
    10 episodes.
  - Children's Day
    Produced programs for 1992 and 1993.
  - China Ballet
    84 tapes.
  - City Scene
    - #101
    - #106
    - #120
    - #124
  - Cold Sassy Tree
    58 tapes including produced programs and work tapes.
  - Community
    including produced programs and work tapes.
  - Computer Workshop
    13 episodes.
  - The Connection
    219 tapes including produced programs and work tapes.
  - Conversations with the Candidates US Senate Texas
    4 tapes.
  - Countdown to War: Saddam Hussein: Threat of War
  - Dino Dig
    10 episodes and work tapes.
  - Dr. Bill Crawford Stress Management
    16 episodes.
  - Election, 1980, 1983, 1985
    10 tapes.
  - The Emigrants
  - Evolution of a Classic
    17 tapes including work tapes and donor appreciation event.
  - Financially Secure Women
    7 episodes.
  - For Pet's Sake, 1986
  - From Chaos to Calm
    17 tapes.
  - Duets for Cannibals
    Including produced programs and work tapes.
  - Focus on Success
    8 episodes.
  - The Friday Local
    - Equal Rights Act / International Women's Year, 1977
  - Green Thought
    12 tapes.
  - Haley's Hints
    9 tapes.
  - HEB TeleVentures Science Quest
    68 tapes including produced programs and work tapes.
  - Homebrew Special / The Home Brewery
    19 tapes including produced programs and work tapes.
  - House Calls: St. Joe Special
    3 episodes and work tapes.
  - Houston 2001: A Livable City?
    - Houston Present and Future: the discontinuities before us, 1978
  - Houston 8 with Ernio Manouse
    101 tapes.
  - Houston Ballet
  - Houston Future
  - Houston Have Your Say!
    27 tapes.
  - Houston Remembers When
    947 tapes including produced programs, work tapes, and interviews.
  - Houston Symphony Orchestra
    51 tapes.
  - HOV
    100 tapes including produced programs and work tapes.
  - Images of America
    Episodes #1-#12.
  - Know Your Rights
    11 episodes.
  - Margaret Ford Show
    - Randy Durlam, Vincent Glocksien, Cynthia Scott
  - Mary Lou's Flip Flop Shop
    790 tapes including produced programs and work tapes.
  - Membership Drive
    114 tapes including produced programs and work tapes.
  - Janie and a Career
    Episodes #1-#18.
  - J.D.'s Journal
    108 tapes including produced programs and work tapes.
  - Junior League
    47 tapes.
  - La Voz Latina
    9 tapes including produced programs and inserts.
    - Lydia Mendoza, July 15, 1980
  - Lazy Gardener with Brenda Smith
    87 tapes.
  - Live at the Woodlands
    3 episodes.
  - Living Smart
    177 tapes including produced programs and work tapes.
  - Lone Star
    Episodes #1-#5, plus two tapes labeled "Party."
  - New Visions, Nuevas Visiones, 1989
    - #605
    - #606
    - #607
    - #608
    - #609
  - Pledge Drives
    7 tapes including work tapes and airchecks.
  - Pop + Lock
  - Profile with Greg Scheinman
    37 tapes.
  - Psychiatry: Helping Families Heal
  - Quilt Festival
  - Red, White & Blue
    122 tapes.
  - Roundtable
    44 tapes.
  - Sports Profiles Beyond the Game
    224 tapes including produced programs and work tapes.
  - Spotlight Showcase
    46 episodes.
  - Superwoman Central
    21 tapes.
  - The Territory
    241 episodes, may include duplicates.
  - Testimonials
  - Tiger Cruise
    60 tapes.
  - Town Meeting
    30 tapes.
  - To Heal A Heart
    76 tapes.
  - U.S. Chronicle with Jim Lehrer
    - Fishing Troubled Waters, 1981
    - Survival in Houston's Public Housing, 1982
  - WD
    355 tapes.
  - Walter Hopps
    Episodes #1-#5.
  - Weeknight Edition
    477 tapes including produced programs and work tapes.
  - West Meets East
    79 tapes.
  - The Writer in Society
    - Donald Barthelme
- University of Houston
  - Cougars Win!, 1972
  - University of Houston Central Campus, Summer 1977
  - Blaffer opening
  - Hugh Roy Cullen Memorial original cuts & surplus
  - Moore Sculpture
  - University of Houston Today
  - UH & downtown color aerials
- Unproduced Elements, B Roll, and Stock Footage
  - Conoco Clean Air Service Car
  - Dance for Downtown Space
  - Election Special 1970
  - Fiesta Hotel
    3 reels
  - Filmed Inserts of Dr. Richard I. Evans
  - Houston downtown street scene, approximately 1957-1958
  - Humble Building under construction
  - Jones Hall at Night
  - KUHT Auction Spots
    8 reels
  - KUHT: Collected Demos, 1953-1957
  - N.S. Savannah at the Port of Houston, May 5, 1964
    No sound on film.
  - Roberto Rosselinni at Rice Media Center
  - Rodeo in the Dome, 1977
  - Salt Grass Trail
    4 reels.
  - School children, houses & people in streets downtown
  - Senator Bentsen speaks on Colonel Bill Bates
  - Sidewalk scenes from above
  - Skyway monorail
  - Source of Oil Pollution
  - S.S. Galveston, March 1969
  - Texas Southern University NAACP Chapter President, approximately 1967
  - Texas Southern University Riots, approximately 1967
  - Texas Stock Roll
    Wharton County: El Campo; Liberty County: Liberty, Cleveland, Dayton; Montgomery County: Historical buildings, Conroe.
- Non-KUHT Productions
  - Another Historic Highlight in the Aerospace Age
    39 reels.
    - SFP 1013A: 1st USAF Bomber Mission in Europe, July 4, 1942
    - SFP 1013AC: B-52s Circle Globe Nonstop, January 18, 1957
    - SFP 1013AD: First American Daylight Bombing of Germany, January 27, 1943
    - SFP 1013AE: First Titan Missile Launch, February 6, 1959
    - SFP 1013AF: Airman Farrell Takes Trip to Moon, February 16, 1958
    - SFP 1013AG: Paratroop drop on Corregidor, February 16, 1945
    - SFP 1013AH: B-25s De-activated, February 23, 1959
    - SFP 1013AI: Lucky Lady Circles Globe Nonstop, March 2, 1949
    - SFP 1013AJ: Project FICON (Fighter Conveyor), March 8, 1955
    - SFP 1013AK: Pioneer V, March 11, 1960
    - SFP 1013AL: Operation Big Slam, March 14, 1960
    - SFP 1013AM: Operation Strangle, March 28, 1944
    - SFP 1013B: Supersonic Military Research Track, July 8, 1955
    - SFP 1013C: Air Force Academy Dedication at Temporary Location, July 11, 1955
    - SFP 1013D: Mass Flight of 58 F-84's, July 17, 1952
    - SFP 1013E: Atlas Nose Cone Recovery, July 21, 1959
    - SFP 1013F: Explorer I Altitude Record, July 28, 1934
    - SFP 1013G: B-47 Nonstop Distance Record, August 4, 1953
    - SFP 1013H: Balloon Altitude Record, August 19, 1957
    - SFP 1013I: First Automatic Aircraft Landing, August 23, 1957
    - SFP 1013J: Jet by Jet Refueling, September 1, 1953
    - SFP 1013K: X-2 Altitude Record, September 7, 1956
    - SFP 1013L: World War I Air Armada, September 12, 1918
    - SFP 1013M: Firs Powered Flight of X-15, September 17, 1959
    - SFP 1013N: Second Successful Thor Launch, October 11, 1957
    - SFP 1013O: Captain Yeager Flies X-1 Faster Than Sound, October 14, 1947
    - SFP 1013P: Four Stage Rocket Fired 2700 Miles Into Space, October 22, 1957
    - SFP 1013Q: Intercontinental Snark Missile Flies 5,000 miles, October 31, 1957
    - SFP 1013R: First Air Delivery of Atlas ICBM, November 3, 1959
    - SFP 1013S: First Aerial Jet Combat, November 8, 1950
    - SFP 1013T: Initial Flight of Supersonic Bomber, November 11, 1956
    - SFP 1013U: First Flight of American Flying Bomb, November 21, 1917
    - SFP 1013V: Chennault's 14th Air Force Bombs Formosa for First Time, November 25, 1943
    - SFP 1013W: Rocket Propelled Sled Attains Record Speed of 632 MPH, December 10, 1954
    - SFP 1013X: Major Bong Becomes America's All Time Ace, December 17, 1944
    - SFP 1013Y: First Controlled Power Airplane Flights, December 17, 1903
    - SFP 1013Z: 8th Air Force Staged Aerial Rail on V-2 Sites, December 24, 1943
    - SFP 1013AA: First Aerial Refueling, January 7, 1929
    - SFP 1013AB: First Bomarc Missile Launch, January 15, 1959
  - NASA
    - Apollo 11 Interviews
    - Color Animation and Blastoff
    - The Flight of Apollo 7
    - Gemini 9
    - Lunar landing sequence 1972
    - Moon
    - NASA - Plans for Manned Space Center
    - NASA - Project Mercury and Project Gemini
    - Skylab III
    - What's New Mission Control?
    - Additional Stock footage
  - Richard Nixon Campaign Ads
    - Nixon - Agnew
    - Great Nation
    - Wrong Road
    - Law & Order 2
    - Vietnam, 1968
      Fuller, Smith & Ross Nixon.
  - Progress Parade
    Production of the American Petroleum Institute.
    - #3 Angler's Paradise, Modern Mythology, and Radioactive Tracers
    - #7 Snakes on Ice, Ribbons of Freedom, Modern Mythology, A Helping Hand
    - #13
  - Screen News Digest
    - China in the 20th Century: the two-headed dragon
    - 7:5 Harnessing the Nile
    - 7:8 Vietnam Report, Focus on Indonesia
    - 12:2 The Changing Face of Eastern Europe, A "New Lock" Behind the Iron Curtain
  - United Way Fundraising Specials
    - General William Westmoreland Message - United Way Version
    - Just An Ordinary Joe, 1982
    - Just Call Me Joe
      United Way of Texas Gulf Coast.
    - United Fund: The Reason Why
  - Individual Programs
    - Alaminos
    - Dollars for Wanda
      Telethon to benefit the Gonzales Warm Springs Foundation.
    - President Dwight D. Eisenhower press conference, January 18, 1961
    - Footprints of the Mayan Gods
    - Glimpses of Masonic History
    - Houston Designs Tomorrow
      Production of the Houston Chamber of Commerce.
    - Houston in Action: Air Pollution Survey First Years Results
    - Jimmy Power's Sports Show #1 Dusty Rhodes Big Bat
    - Life in the Far East
      Production of Coronet Film.
    - Mexican-American - A Quest for Equality
    - Newsreel, 1944
      Paramount
    - Puerto Rico: Portal of Riches
      Production of the Waterman Steamship Corporation.
    - Red China: Peking and the Commune
    - Retailer Reaches Out
      Production of the Humble Oil Company.
    - The School Dropout Problem - Pesident Kennedy
      The Advertising Council
    - Singapore, Malaya - New States in the South
    - Southwest Indians of Early America
    - Stripper Fishers of Men LaPort
    - The Twentieth Century: Deep in the Heart of Houston, February 16, 1964
      Production of CBS News.
    - USS Platemakers to the Southwest
    - Voyage from Antiquity